Guide to the Bronson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bronson Family papers
1753-1898
MS 103
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, legal and financial papers, a diary and miscellaneous items of the Bronson family of Washington, Connecticut. The largest part of the papers are those of Moseley Virgil Bronson (1806-1890), documenting his career as an officer of the Connecticut militia and as a teacher in New York and Connecticut. Of particular interest are the letters of Edna Moseley Todd, who moved to Virginia in 1821, and whose letters to various members of the family describe her life as a mother and school teacher, as well as offering comments on slavery and abolitionism. Also in the papers is the diary of Maria N. Fowler Ford, recording her experience as a physician's wife in Hawaii (1854-1858) and in New York and Connecticut (1858-1861). There are also miscellaneous papers of the Hollister family.
Bronson family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Clarence W. Bronson between 1943 and 1949.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by Bronson family members.
Index of Correspondents
Allen, F. L., 1877 Sep 6
Andrews, John P., 1853 Apr 15-1863 Oct 14, undated
Baldwin, H., 1851 Mar 25
Beach, S. Y., 1843 Aug 18
Beeman, Oscar E., 1891 Dec 7-1902 Jan 8
Bronson, Bethiah (Virgil), 1813 Oct 4-1819 Feb 19
Bronson, Edwin, 1868 Dec 5-1874 Nov 9
Bronson, Ephraim, 1813 Jan 20-1819 Jan 29
Bronson, Harriett E., Undated
Bronson, Ira Virgil, 1829 Dec 25-1851 Jun 8
Bronson, Jacob, 1819 Jul 2
Bronson, Martha A., 1857 Dec 4-1858 Dec 4, undated
Bronson, Moseley Virgil, 1838 Apr 10-1851 Mar 31
Bronson, Susan M., 1831 Jun 26
Bronson, Walter Whittlesey, 1871 Mar 8-1902 Jun 12
Bronson, William Clark, 1832 Jan 21-1839 Dec 30
Brooks, George, 1838 Sep 3
Calhoun, Sarah, Undated
Calhoun, Seth, 1834 Feb 11
Cogshall, William S., 1838 Feb 15
Cooper, Daniel S., 1865 Apr 18-1879 Jan 8
Curtis, Eli, 1838 Jul 2
Dimock, Marvin W., 1852 Jan 13/14
Doughty, Joseph C., [1840?] Aug 31-1850 Feb 21
Hammond, Charles, 1837 Mar 21
Hayes, Gordon, 1842 Oct 15
Hemingway, Merrit, 1838 Jun 8
Hickox, Ithiel, 1838 Oct 30
Leavitt, William W., 1827 Dec 17-1838 Jun 12
Moseley, W. G., 1877 May 23
Peck, D. A., 1839 Feb 18
Phelps, General, 1838 Apr 23
Robertson, George B., 1838 May 9
Smith, A[ugustus], 1869 Feb 15
Smith, Ebenezer C., 1828 Apr 17
Smith, J. Homer, 1839 Feb 16
Sperry, H G, 1835 May 28
Sunbury, Mrs. James B., 1853 Apr 12
Todd, Edna (Moseley), 1821 Nov 1-1846 Dec 19
Wheaton, J. B., 1845 May 22
Whittlesey, Gould Camp, 1898 Jan 28
Whittlesey, Sarah Deming, 1870 Mar 26
Wood, Morgan L., 1834 Nov 30-1835 Jan 10
Scope and Contents
The Bronson Family Papers, 1753-1902, consist of ten inches of correspondence, legal and financial papers, a diary, and miscellaneous items related mainly to the Bronson family of Washington, Conn. The largest segment of the papers concerns Moseley Virgil Bronson (1806-1890), son of Dr. Ira Virgil Bronson (1788-1866) and Sarah Ann (Moseley) Bronson (1775-1862).¹ There are also papers of his father, his father's parents, his mother's Moseley relations, and his brothers and sisters. Finally, there are a few non-family papers of the Hollister family and Maria N. (Fowler) Ford.
All the correspondence is in a single chronological sequence consisting mainly of these components (the principal place of residence being Washington, Conn., unless otherwise stated): › Ephraim and Bethiah Bronson of Locke, N.Y., and Groton, Conn., to their son and daughter-in-law, Ira V. and Sarah A. (Moseley) Bronson, 1813-1819 › Edna (Moseley) Todd of Richmond and Prince Edward County, Va., to various members of the Bronson family, 1821-1833, 1838-1846 › Family (mainly Ira V. and William C. Bronson) to Moseley V. Bronson, living in various places in N.Y. and Conn., 1827-1869 › Martha Bronson, at the State Normal School in New Britain, Conn., to her parents, Mr. and Mrs. Moseley V. Bronson, 1857-1858 › Miscellaneous family and non-family, 1871-1902
The rest of the papers are filed alphabetically under the names of the persons to whom they belonged. Increase Moseley (1712-1795) is represented by a volume of his proceedings as justice of the peace in Woodbury, Conn., between 1753 and 1781. The papers of Moseley V. Bronson document his career as an officer of the Connecticut militia (12th Infantry Regt., Co. 5) and a teacher in New York and Connecticut. Ira V. Bronson, Lucy Ann (Whittlesey) Bronson, Susan M. Bronson, Walter W. Bronson, and William C. Bronson are represented by small quantities of miscellaneous material including legal and financial papers, records of teaching, and memorabilia. The diary of Maria N. (Fowler) Ford is a record of her experience as a physician's wife in Hawaii, 1854-1858, and in New York and Connecticut, 1858-1861. The unidentified papers include legal and financial papers, farm accounts, and some religious music.
¹Dr. Bronson was born in Locke, N.Y., studied medicine with Dr. Everest in Simsbury, Conn., and settled in Washington, Conn., in 1804. The following year he married Sarah Ann Moseley (1775-1862), daughter of Abner Moseley and grand-daughter of Increase Moseley (1712-1795), justice of the peace in Woodbury, Conn.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Agriculture -- Connecticut; Armed Forces; Education; Families; House furnishings; Law; Missionaries -- United States; Music; Schools -- Connecticut; Schools -- New York (State); Slavery -- United States; Women -- Education; Asia; Connecticut; Hawaii -- Description and travel; Virginia -- History; Washington (Conn.); Diaries; Clergy; Educators; Physicians; Soldiers; Bronson, Bethiah Virgil; Bronson, Ephraim; Bronson, Ira Virgil, 1778-1866; Bronson, Lucy Ann Whittlesey, 1820-; Bronson, Moseley Virgil, 1806-1890; Bronson, Sarah Ann Moseley, 1775-1862; Bronson, Susan M., 1814-; Bronson, Walter Whittlesey, 1848-; Bronson, William Clark, 1811-1877; Calhoun, Sarah; Calhoun, Seth; Cooper, Daniel S.; Dimock, Marvin W.; Moseley, Increase, 1712-1795; Nettleton, Martha Augusta Bronson, 1841-; Smith, J. Augustus; Todd, Edna Moseley, 1796-1848; Branson family; Hollis family; Mosley family; First Church (Washington, Conn.); United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry, 12th Regiment
- Inventory, 1753-1781, 1804-1898
  - Correspondence, 1813-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
  - Bronson, Ira Virgil (1778-1866): lease, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bronson, Lucy Ann (Whittlesey) (1820-)
    - Funeral sermon for Deacon Whittlesey, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Legal and financial papers, 1864-1899 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - School essays, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mementoes from friends, photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bronson, Moseley Virgil (1806-1890)
    - Military papers
      - Rosters, inspection returns, and enlistment certificates, 1824-1837 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Commissions, 1832-1838 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Regimental orders, 1835-1837 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Orders to non-commissioned officers, 1835-1837 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - School papers
      - Tuition records, 1831-1850 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Teaching certificates, 1827-1853 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Accounts for board and other financial papers, 1834-1854 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Students' attendance records, 1839-1859 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Legal and financial papers, 1835-1877 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bronson, Susan M. (1814-): inventory of household goods, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bronson, Walter Whittlesey
    - Essays, 1865, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Teaching certificates, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Records of students' attendance, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bronson, William C. (1811-1877)
    - Notes re: religious experience, 1831, 1834, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Account book, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Financial and legal papers, 1836-1864 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Essay, "Upon Politics", [pre-1837] (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Sunday school reports and lists of pupils, 1861-1862, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Proprietors' accounts for the District 5 school, 1861-1863 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - List of apple trees, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ford, Maria N. (Fowler): diary, 1854-1861 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hollister family: legal and financial papers, 1803-1876 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Moseley, Increase (1712-1795): records of the Justice's Court of Woodbury, Connecticut, 1753-1781 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified
    - Connecticut census (printed, with unrelated annotations), 1774 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Farm accounts, 1804-1814 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Deeds, 1805-1878 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers, 1834-1867, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Records of early-morning frost, 1835 June-August (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Music, lists of hymns, 1835-1836, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Draft vote of church members to censure Augustus Smith, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Diary, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Genealogical notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)